<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Rigmarole Blog</title><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/feeds/tip-of-the-day.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chris-lesage.github.io/</id><updated>2014-07-31T15:45:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Quickly Select and Isolate Curves in Maya’s Graph Editor</title><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/tip-of-the-day/quickly-select-and-isolate-curves-in-mayas-graph-editor/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-07-31T15:45:00-04:00</published><author><name>Chris Lesage</name></author><id>tag:chris-lesage.github.io,2014-07-31:tip-of-the-day/quickly-select-and-isolate-curves-in-mayas-graph-editor/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here is a simple but powerful animation tip in Autodesk Maya. This is an essential tip for animators and&amp;nbsp;riggers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Maya, let&amp;#8217;s say you are working in the &lt;strong&gt;Graph Editor&lt;/strong&gt; with dozens or hundreds of objects, and you need to select and edit only the &lt;em&gt;translateY&lt;/em&gt; curves. Here is how to select them&amp;nbsp;easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply select translateY in the &lt;strong&gt;Channel Box&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="select_curves_by_channel_box" src="http://chrislesage.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/select_curves_by_channel_box1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will automatically select and isolate all the translateY curves for all selected objects in the &lt;strong&gt;Graph Editor&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="select_curves_in_graph_editor" src="http://chrislesage.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/select_curves_by_channel_box2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, you can also use Shift to highlight multiple channels or Ctrl to remove channels from the highlighted&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first noticed this when I was editing 240 Driven Key curves for a mechanical prop rig. In the past I would have tediously selected all the curves in the left side channel list in the graph editor. I&amp;#8217;m not sure when this feature was added to Maya, but I only noticed it after years of doing it the slow&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Channel Box is a major time saver! Tell your&amp;nbsp;animators!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="animation"></category><category term="graph-editor"></category><category term="maya"></category></entry><entry><title>Use K to Easily Navigate Your Maya Timeline</title><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/tip-of-the-day/use-k-to-easily-navigate-your-maya-timeline/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-07T15:17:00-05:00</published><author><name>Chris Lesage</name></author><id>tag:chris-lesage.github.io,2012-03-07:tip-of-the-day/use-k-to-easily-navigate-your-maya-timeline/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are tons of features and hotkeys and hidden marking menus in Maya that are extremely useful but surprisingly seldom known. While everyone is talking about big new features, these underdogs can easily be&amp;nbsp;forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just started a &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;tip of the day&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; with my animators at work because I realized that there are lot of these things that they aren&amp;#8217;t aware of, but being a major geek, I&amp;#8217;ve read through the help docs like a crime-thriller novel. (It turns out the Zoom Tool did it.) Today&amp;#8217;s was such a hit that I thought I&amp;#8217;d start posting some of the best ones&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tip of the&amp;nbsp;day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hold down &amp;#8216;K&amp;#8217; and drag in the viewport. Your timeline will scrub as if you were dragging down on the time slider. Middle-mouse drag and your characters will stay in place for copying keyframes. (Again, same as the time slider.) This also works in the graph editor and the dope&amp;nbsp;sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Customize the&amp;nbsp;Hotkey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hotkey editor this feature can be found under Tools &amp;gt; TimeDraggerToolActivate. This means that you can map it to another key if you wish. You could also invoke the context in your own custom &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;tools.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="animtip"></category><category term="hotkeys"></category><category term="maya"></category><category term="rigtip"></category></entry></feed>