<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Rigmarole Blog</title><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/feeds/writing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chris-lesage.github.io/</id><updated>2013-11-18T15:45:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>A Manual Progress Bar in Scrivener</title><link href="http://chris-lesage.github.io/writing/a-manual-progress-bar-in-scrivener/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-18T15:45:00-05:00</published><author><name>Chris Lesage</name></author><id>tag:chris-lesage.github.io,2013-11-18:writing/a-manual-progress-bar-in-scrivener/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I want to show you a cool trick for making semi-graphical Status labels in the writing program Scrivener, and then explain some of the reasons you might want to do this. I used it to make a manual progress&amp;nbsp;bar.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="scrivener_status_screenshot" src="http://chrislesage.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/scrivener_status_screenshot.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php"&gt;Scrivener&lt;/a&gt; and Markdown to write my blog, as well as writing documentation and training material. If you don&amp;#8217;t know, It is a structured writing program - usually used for novels, scripts, screenplays and academic writing - which can output to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;, Markdown, LaTeX, ebook, Final Draft, Word formats and&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So it is also a great tool for blogging, research, course notes or technical documentation for&amp;nbsp;software.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m currently transitioning the help docs for a Maya plugin I&amp;#8217;m working on from Google Docs into Scrivener. The revisions/snapshots and structured nature of Scrivener make it ideal for documents which need frequent&amp;nbsp;updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrivener already has a progress bar which is based on target word-count. That&amp;#8217;s fine if you are aiming for a particular length in a long novel or an essay with a word target. &lt;strong&gt;However, you don&amp;#8217;t always know what your target is before-hand.&lt;/strong&gt; Especially when you are writing a lot of shorter documents such a blog posts, course notes, technical documentation or training&amp;nbsp;tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I prefer having manual control.&lt;/strong&gt; So to simulate a percentage progress bar in Scrivener I created 6 &amp;#8220;Status:&amp;#8221; options using the following Unicode&amp;nbsp;characters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: If you are setting this up, you don&amp;#8217;t have to enter the number codes. Just copy/paste the characters in &amp;#8220;Project -&amp;gt; &amp;#8220;Meta-Data Settings&amp;#8221; and then click on the &amp;#8220;Status&amp;#8221; tab. You can paste the character there to make these statuses. The numbers are there only for reference in case they aren&amp;#8217;t displaying properly in your&amp;nbsp;browser.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;▢ - White square with rounded corners
Unicode number: U+25A2

█ - Full block
Unicode number: U+2588

░ - Light shade
Unicode number: U+2591

▒ - Medium shade
Unicode number: U+2592

▢▢▢▢▢ 0%
█▢▢▢▢ 20%
██▢▢▢ 40%
███▢▢ 60%
████▢ 80%
█████ 100%
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if you prefer increments of&amp;nbsp;25%:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;▢▢▢▢ 0%
█▢▢▢ 25%
██▢▢ 50%
███▢ 75%
████ 100%
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some&amp;nbsp;extras:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;░░░░░░░ done (published)
▒▒✘✘✘▒▒ scrapped
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://chrislesage.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/scrivener_unicode_status.jpg"&gt;Click here to see the image if your browser isn&amp;#8217;t displaying the unicode characters&amp;nbsp;properly.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s how this looks in Outline&amp;nbsp;mode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="scrivener_unicode_screenshot" src="http://chrislesage.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/scrivener_unicode_screenshot.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So Why Do&amp;nbsp;This?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes your progress depends on elements &lt;strong&gt;that are not related to the word-count&lt;/strong&gt;, such as data, graphs, multimedia elements that another designer is creating, or any other amount of tasks that may need&amp;nbsp;doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a big difference between &amp;#8220;finished writing&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;finished editing&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;ready to&amp;nbsp;publish&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you may have a lot of words or notes that need a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOT&lt;/span&gt; of editing. Your rough notes shouldn&amp;#8217;t necessarily count towards your progress. Maybe you will write 5000 words just to edit it down to 2500. Some days you will end up with less words, &lt;strong&gt;but you are still technically making forward&amp;nbsp;progress.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So using &amp;#8220;Status&amp;#8221; graphically is a way to &lt;strong&gt;manually&lt;/strong&gt; set your progress, in a sort of eye-catching&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also sort by status with this. The black bars go in the correct order, and the &amp;#8220;done&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;scrapped&amp;#8221; shaded bars go to the bottom, but above&amp;nbsp;0%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to search for other unicode characters that you can use, &lt;a href="http://unicode-table.com/"&gt;check out this unicode website&lt;/a&gt;. You can also copy/paste a character into this website to find out the unicode&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bet you can think of some other ideas to make some graphical reminders or just make your status labels more meaningful to you. Give it a try and let me know what you think in the&amp;nbsp;comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="#98" title="2013-11-19 10:24:05"&gt;Chris Lesage&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Hey everyone. I got a few comments asking to be more specific about how to set this up. Here are some more detailed steps if you want to set this up in Scrivener. Note: All you have to do is copy and paste the unicode characters directly. &lt;strong&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t have to enter the number code&amp;nbsp;anywhere.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy (Ctrl-C) the squares from my post or from&amp;nbsp;unicode-table.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Scrivener menubar go to &amp;#8220;Project&amp;#8221; -&amp;gt; &amp;#8220;Meta-Data Settings&amp;#8221; and then click on the &amp;#8220;Status&amp;#8221; tab. This is where you can add your own custom Labels and Statuses or arbitrary&amp;nbsp;meta-data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit the &amp;#8220;+&amp;#8221; button to add a new Status and paste (Ctrl-V) the special characters right there. The unicode numbers were just there for reference in case the graphics weren&amp;#8217;t showing up properly on anybody&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="#106" title="2013-12-14 05:09:05"&gt;Chloe Carson&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Hey this is fantastic, thanks so much! I imagine I could use these on Squarespace as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="#101" title="2013-11-27 13:07:31"&gt;ady coles&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Hi Chris, This is great! If you don&amp;#8217;t mind, i would like to include a link to this article from my &amp;#8216;scrivener resources&amp;#8217; page. (http://acol.es/stScrivener)&amp;nbsp;Ady&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="#102" title="2013-11-27 13:33:22"&gt;Chris Lesage&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Hi Ady, yes please feel free. Thanks for the&amp;nbsp;comment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scrivener"></category><category term="tools"></category><category term="writing"></category></entry></feed>